<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<program_description xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.decision-deck.org/ws/_downloads/description.xsd">
    <program provider="PUT"
        name="extremeRankingAnalysis"
        displayName="extremeRankingAnalysis"
        version="1.0" />
    <documentation>
        <description>Finds the best and worst possible positions of alternatives in the final ranking taking into consideration all value functions that are compatible with the preference information.</description>
        <contact>Pawel Rychly (pawelrychly@gmail.com).</contact>
    </documentation>
    
    
    <parameters>
        <input id="alternatives"
            name="alternatives"
            displayName="alternatives"
            isoptional="0">
            <documentation>
                <description>The list of all considered alternatives. The input value should be a valid XMCDA document whose main tag is alternatives. Each alternative may be described using a two attributes: id and name. While the first one denotes a machine readable name, the second represents a human readable name.</description>
            </documentation>
            <xmcda tag="alternatives">
                <![CDATA[
                    <alternatives>
                        <alternative id="%1" name="%2" />
                        [...]
                    </alternatives>
                    ]]>
            </xmcda>
        </input>
        
        <input id="criteria"
            name="criteria"
            displayName="criteria"
            isoptional="0">
            <documentation>
                <description>A list of all considered criteria. The input value should be a valid XMCDA document whose main tag is criteria. It is assumed that the preference direction should be set on max.</description>
            </documentation>
            <xmcda tag="criteria">
                <![CDATA[
                    <criteria>
                        <criterion id="%1" name="%1">
                            <scale>
                                <quantitative>
                                    <preferenceDirection>max</preferenceDirection>
                                </quantitative>
                            </scale>
                        </criterion>
                        [...]
                    </criteria>
                    ]]>
            </xmcda>
        </input>
        
        <input id="performances"
            name="performances"
            displayName="performances"
            isoptional="0">
            <documentation>
                <description>Description of values on criteria for different alternatives. It is required to provide the IDs of both criteria and alternatives described previously. The input value should be provided as a valid XMCDA document whose main tag is performanceTable</description>
            </documentation>
            <xmcda tag="performanceTable">
                <![CDATA[
                    <performanceTable>
                        <alternativePerformances> 
                            <alternativeID>%1</alternativeID>
                            <performance>
                                <criterionID>%2</criterionID>
                                <value>
                                    <real>%3</real>
                                </value>
                            </performance>
                            [...]
                        </alternativePerformances>
                        [...]
                    </performanceTable>
                    ]]>
            </xmcda>
        </input>
        
        
        <input id="preferences" name="preferences" displayName="preferences"
            isoptional="1">
            <documentation>
                <description>Set of pairwise comparisons of alternatives that constitutes the form of the preference information. For a pair of alternatives three types of comparisons are supported. These are the strict preference, weak preference and indifference. The input value should be provided as a valid XMCDA document whose main tag is alternativesComparisons. For each type of comparison, a separate alternativesComparisons tag should be used. Within these groups a mentioned types are denoted using a comparisonType tag by respectively strict, weak and indif label. Comparisons should be provided as a pairs of alternatives ids.</description>
            </documentation>
            <xmcda tag="alternativesComparisons">
                <![CDATA[
                    <alternativesComparisons>
                        <comparisonType>
                            %1<!-- type of preference: strong, weak, or indif -->
                        </comparisonType>
                        <pairs>
                            <pair>
                                <initial>
                                    <alternativeID>%2</alternativeID>
                                </initial>
                                <terminal>
                                    <alternativeID>%3</alternativeID>
                                </terminal>
                            </pair>
                            [...]
                        </pairs>
                    </alternativesComparisons>
                    [...]
                    ]]>
            </xmcda>
        </input>

        <input id="intensities-of-preferences" name="intensities-of-preferences" displayName="intensities-of-preferences"
            isoptional="1">
            
            <documentation>
                <description>Set of comparisons of intensities of preference relations that constitutes the form of the preference information. For a pair of preference relations three types of comparisons are supported. These are the strict preference, weak preference and indifference. The input value should be provided as a valid XMCDA document whose main tag is alternativesComparisons. For each type of comparison, a separate alternativesComparisons tag should be used. Within these groups a mentioned types are denoted using a comparisonType tag by respectively strict, weak and indif label. Comparisons should be provided as a pairs of two elementary sets of alternatives ids. The following form is expected:</description>
            </documentation>
            <xmcda tag="alternativesComparisons">
                <![CDATA[
                    <alternativesComparisons>
                        <comparisonType>%1</comparisonType>
                        <pairs>
                            <pair>
                                <initial>
                                    <alternativesSet>
                                        <element>
                                            <alternativeID>%2</alternativeID>
                                        </element>
                                        <element>
                                            <alternativeID>%3</alternativeID>
                                        </element>
                                    </alternativesSet>
                                </initial>
                                <terminal>
                                    <alternativesSet>
                                        <element>
                                            <alternativeID>%4</alternativeID>
                                        </element>
                                        <element>
                                            <alternativeID>%5</alternativeID>
                                        </element>
                                    </alternativesSet>
                                </terminal>
                            </pair>
                            [...]
                        </pairs>
                    </alternativesComparisons>
                    [...] 
                    ]]>
            </xmcda>
        </input>

        <input id="rank-related-requirements" name="rank-related-requirements" displayName="rank-related-requirements"
            isoptional="1">
            
            <documentation>
                <description>Set of rank-related requirements that constitutes the form of the preference information. In other words it is a set of  ranges of possible positions in the final ranking for a chosen alternatives. The input value should be provided as a valid XMCDA document whose main tag is alternativesValues. Each requirement should contain both an id of chosen alternative and pair of values that denotes the desired range. These informations should be provided within a separate alternativesValue tag.</description>
            </documentation>
            <xmcda tag="alternativesValues">
                <![CDATA[
                    <alternativesValues>
                        <alternativeValue>
                            <alternativeID>%1</alternativeID>
                            <value>
                                <interval>
                                    <lowerBound><integer>%2</integer></lowerBound>
                                    <upperBound><integer>%3</integer></upperBound>
                                </interval>
                            </value>
                        </alternativeValue>
                        [...]
                    </alternativesValues>
                    ]]>
            </xmcda>
        </input>
        
        <input id="characteristic-points" name="characteristic-points" displayName="characteristic points"
            isoptional="1">
            
            <documentation>
                <description>A set of values associated with the criteria. This input allows to determine what type of value function should be used for the particular criterion. For each criterion that has an associated greater than one value, a piecewise linear value function is used. In this case, the mentioned value denotes a number of characteristic points of this value function. For criteria that are not listed in this file, or which values are lower than two uses a general value function. The input value should be provided as a valid XMCDA document whose main tag is criteriaValues. Each element should contain both an id of the criterion, and value tag.</description>
            </documentation>
            <xmcda tag="criteriaValues">
                <![CDATA[
                     <criteriaValues>
                        <criterionValue>
                            <criterionID>%1</criterionID>
                            <value>
                                <integer>%2</integer>
                            </value>
                        </criterionValue>
                        [...]
                    </criteriaValues>
                    ]]>
            </xmcda>
        </input>
        
        <input id="parameters" name="parameters" displayName="parameters"
            isoptional="0">
            <documentation>
                <description>Single boolean value. Determines whether to use sctrictly increasing (true) or monotonously increasing (false) value functions</description>
            </documentation>
            <xmcda tag="methodParameters">
                <![CDATA[
                     <methodParameters>
                        <parameter name="strict">
                            <value>
                                <boolean>%1</boolean>
                            </value>
                        </parameter>
                    </methodParameters>
                    ]]>
            </xmcda>
            <gui status="alwaysGUI">
                <entry id="%1" type="boolean" displayName="Use strictly increasing value functions?">
                    <defaultValue>false</defaultValue>
                </entry>
            </gui>
        </input>
        
        <output id="best-ranking"
            name="best-ranking"
            displayName="best ranking">
            <documentation>
                <description>The best possible ranking positions that may be achieved by the alternatives taking into consideration all value functions that are compatible with the preference information. The returned value is a XMCDA document whose main tag is alternativesValues.</description>
            </documentation>
            <xmcda tag="alternativesValues">
                <![CDATA[
                    <alternativesValues>
						<alternativeValue>
							<alternativeID>[...]</alternativeID>
							<value>
								<real>[...]</real>
							</value>
						 </alternativeValue>
                        [...]
                    </alternativesValues>
                    ]]>
            </xmcda>
        </output>
		
		<output id="worst-ranking"
            name="worst-ranking"
            displayName="worst ranking">
            
            <documentation>
                <description>The worst possible ranking positions that may be achieved by the alternatives taking into consideration all value functions that are compatible with the preference information. The returned value is a XMCDA document whose main tag is alternativesValues.</description>
            </documentation>
            <xmcda tag="alternativesValues">
                <![CDATA[
                    <alternativesValues>
						<alternativeValue>
							<alternativeID>[...]</alternativeID>
							<value>
								<real>[...]</real>
							</value>
						 </alternativeValue>
                        [...]
                    </alternativesValues>
                    ]]>
            </xmcda>
        </output>

        <output id="messages"
            name="messages"
            displayName="messages">
            
            <documentation>
                <description>A list of messages generated by the algorithm.</description>
            </documentation>
            <xmcda tag="methodMessages"/>
        </output>
        
    </parameters>
</program_description>

